[Music]
hi my name is Andrew Sweeney and welcome
to my podcast today I'd like to speak
about one of my personal heroes and
somebody who greatly affected me in my
life especially I think in the last 10
years but also all through my adult life
and that is Leonard Cohen
so one letter Cohen passed last year
around the same time Trump was elected I
spend about a few months writing about
his music in his words miss lyrics in
his poetry and so I'm gonna read you
some of what I wrote so this one I
called meditations on Leonard Cohen and
I called the entire project my landlord
because I very briefly lived in a
building owned by Leonard Cohen back in
Montreal in the late 90s meditations on
Leonard Cohen number one I want to write
a different kind of book about Leonard
Cohen nothing biographical or academic
but something that that would emulate
and mirror the music so what kind of
book would that be well certainly the
words would have to be well chosen the
meaning compressed the form tight
there'd have to be a good simple melody
it would have to be minimalistic
suggests more than it reveals it would
be highly enjoyable and yet at the same
time provocative it would not fear to
enter dark landscapes of the soul
it's philosophical pessimism would evoke
hope and goodwill from the knowledge
that Things Fall Apart would arise a
broken hallelujah perhaps I would add a
choir of female backup singers
not sure how to achieve that in the pros
yet so even though this is an amateur
work in other words written without
promise of money but for sheer love of a
man I'm not up writing about mr. Cohan
without aim or vision each chapter is
meant to be like a song and prose rather
than a journalistic expose a compressed
and suggestive tune much is left unsaid
and unspoken and much is implied again I
think this is harmonious with Leonard's
own style and method I've got no
interest in gossip nor do I pretend to
be without subjectivity here
as much as I'm the fan I aspire to meet
mr. Cohen as a fellow songwriter and
writer this is a highly personal and
passionate conversation with the works
of an elder it's written or the fools
freedom I skipped the Hollywood gossip
and go straight for the gold his works
these essays are my way of humming along
with the songs but they also seek to be
prose songs in themselves as a
songwriter I work on the art of
compression and try to pack as much
meaning as possible into a limited
formal space you could also say that
these are a series of unrequited love
letters in the spirit of the troubadour
Cohen said somewhere that he didn't
consider himself precisely a poet but a
troubadour though he was being fairly
modest I know what he means
artistically I am Cohen's devoted
student personally I think of him as a
Jewish father to my boy soul on the
subject of Leonard the Jew I've done a
brief study of certain aspects of
Judaism which have affected his work
without knowing very much about the
Jewish religion I've come into contact
by serendipity with Cohen's last Jewish
teacher and self declared heretic rabbi
yaakov
liebe Jaco Ain who has been instrumental
in writing this while writing I listen
to the rabbi's podcast and his fiery
sermons on the Zohar and a richness of
insights flowed into these writings from
that strangely enough I also met the
late
Kiyo zan Joshu Suzuki Roshi a couple of
times at malt I'd Mount Baldy
in Montreal in the late 1990s
a fiery Zen teacher from there inside
tradition who lived to the ripe old age
of 107 both of these men are beings who
are rare challenging unpopular to many
the one meets only by serendipity chance
or blessings as far as I can see these
are some of the secret sources of
Cohen's genius and I am so fortunate to
have felt their influence if only a
little these chance meetings had an aura
of fate and Cohen as teachers are always
on my mind for one reason or another in
Zen which Cohen and myself less
intensely studied for years there is
something called a tatio it's a bit
different than a sermon in the sense
that it is spoken without meaning to
convince or convert at a show is a short
and heartfelt exposition where words
arise spontaneously I conceived of these
writings in that vein if scholarly or
theological elements come up they are
always secondary to a deeper message
being transmitted and the speaker of
taisho never knows what he is going to
say before he speaks there is no overall
plan and that is how I have written this
I my hope is that these words will allow
people to enter Cohen's work more deeply
as writing this has done for me like
William Blake Leonard Cohen's lyrics
contain a code language revealing a
deeper world little golden keys for
instance when he talks about boogie
street
he's speaking of samsara or the wheel of
birth and death
unlike the modernist James Joyce or TS
Eliot tradition is enlivened by the
language and forms of popular culture in
Cohen's work nobody has ever told us
what booby Street is for he sings
perhaps because nobody ever can poetry
exists to reveal mystery rather than
give us an explanation our prescription
for how to live in short this is a
dialogue with Cohen's work a way to
uncover its profundities and joys and to
wrestle with his difficulties my main
method of research has simply been to
listen to these songs and let them move
through me often I write after
meditation which helps me open to what
the bard is revealing to me the more I
uncover the more surprises I find by
this man who has haunted me since you as
my slum landlord in Montreal way back in
the 1990s I don't know why they sent me
here to raise my voice in song sings
Leonard Coyne similarily I don't know
why I'm compelled to speak about his
works who knows why we do what we do why
we fall in love for instance in falling
we cannot reason we can only fall deeper
I can only say I have found Cohen an
inexhaustible well and I hope that more
people in future generations they will
be lucky enough to fall into that sweet
well so this is called number zero and
it starts with a quote from Bob Dylan
Leonard I would say that you were number
one and I'm number zero Bob Dylan when
people say they find the music of
Leonard Cohen depressing I reach for my
shotgun metaphorically speaking another
friend of mine called his music dark
which annoys me even more Bono once sent
the Cohens music is brightly colored
which is more just those who find
Leonard Cohen dark and depressing just
haven't heard the smile on his music or
notice just how deep that smile goes a
thousand kisses deep perhaps Leonard
Cohen didn't make serious music until he
was over 30 so it's normal that his
music appeals to adults not those stuck
in permanent adolescence he was always
considered more European than American
in Europe older artists are beloved and
the cult of youth is not so pronounced
American pop culture sacrifices its
young to the Maalik of drugs and fame
well the very few rise above Leonard
Cohen was a little different firstly
because he was Canadian and already
quite mature when he was first noticed
he had already lived so much and avoided
many deathly traps that fame provides a
young and unformed person Cohen's great
songs are bitter and sweet in equal
measures they have a supreme balance of
taste like a good vintage the music is
always subordinate to what is being said
unlike pop music which privileges
sensation over meaning folk music can be
sickly sweet message oriented or
nihilistic and singer songwriters are
often known to wallow in narcissism the
Cohen is on another level
he is detached enough to make you laugh
engaged enough to cut you to pieces he
knows he is putting on a show and how
did he know 'he's how to make it real at
the same time that is why there is no
better vocal music to put on after
making
in that state of infinite wariness and
receptivity sometimes it's better listen
to artists and critics when talking
about other artists Bob Dylan was the
first to notice that hallelujah was a
hallelujah was a great song he got it
right he noticed that while people talk
about Cohen's words all the time they
missed the brilliance of his melody and
understated his quality as a musician
the melodies are deep and subtle which
explains our lasting power and unlike
most singers Cohen's voice became richer
and fuller over time as those
unnecessary high notes fell away some
people say that Cohen has no voice but
they don't notice how deep in the belly
it really is it's a purely intimate
voice whispering in your ear like the
talking that goes on and lovemaking
again it's no surprise that when Leonard
Cohen was a young man he was a master at
hypnosis he is hypnotic but also highly
wakeful and connected to the heart
Cohen songs contain that 3:00 in the
morning wakefulness for those moments
avoid in Atonement
I may be uniquely qualified to say
something about Leonard Cohen's music
for a couple of reasons for one thing I
know something of the landscape of his
youth coincidentally again I lived for
10 years in his old neighborhood in
Montreal and briefly in his old house by
the Portuguese park off maryanne which
was a Zen temple at the time for a few
years I practiced RINs eyes in in the
same lineage a lineage that is both
austere and severe but which also has an
unsurpassed sense of humor on top of
that I received the same degree as Cohen
in literature at McGill University the
parallels are striking in my choice of
hobbies Zen writing song it's as if I
have been unconsciously following or
imitating him all my life
in fact when I met him in the 1990s I
had little idea of his effect on me I
was even surprised when her reviewer
described my first album called monotone
which was named for a style as
enchanting as Cohen asked his influence
wasn't apparent to me at the time but
grew on me over the years oh how well I
know those ragged and poetic nights of
Montreal Bohemia as a young 20-something
I lingered in the same open mic cabarets
that Montreal is famous for opening for
such singers as Rufus Wainwright
Godspeed you black Emperor who have
since achieved a measure of Fame in the
late 1990s before internet took hold
there was a lively scene there Cohen has
said that Montreal was in some ways more
vibrant than the bigger cosmopolitan
places like New York perhaps because of
the severe cold there was a lot of
warmth generated in the art scene
Montreal was a perfect place to be free
and irresponsible and to make art and to
get out of the rat race but this coin
once wrote
beware of Montreal in winter it will
bring everything down the pull of that
brightly color of world the woman and
the poetry the disillusion that
engenders are bound to lead one to
religion or ruin I crossed paths with
Leonard Cohen once at the Zen Center
being an ambitious young songwriter I
had recorded a demo cassette which I
passed on to him Leonard always the
perfect gentleman graciously accepted my
demo entitled soon soon and said a good
title he declined my invitation to a
show that night and told me he had
previous engagements but the next day he
asked me how it was a tough gig I
replied I played to a half a room with a
bad sound system where the expresso
machine drowned out my unliked Cousteau
guitar I've had my share of tough gigs
he said making us feel on the same
even though he was an established world
superstar and I was watching dishes to
pay the rent and playing music in a
pizza parlor our meeting was full of
warmth the same warmth as his music for
the man and the music were the same
combination of warmth intelligence and
wit those songs are not depressing in
the least
they are the antidote depression during
the Zen retreat Leonard was just another
face in a sea of faces meditating in his
dark robe looking like a very exhausted
old man I could hear his voice chanting
got a got a para got a possum got a
Bodhi swaahaa which means gone gone gone
to the other Shore a voice that was
pronounced even in that setting few
people know how that Japanese Channing
affected his vocal stylings and the hard
work he did in zen temples or much about
the secret life he sang about like me he
washed dishes but voluntarily not
because he needed to pay the rent
perhaps he submitted to all that arduous
hard work as a counterbalance to the
luxury of being a star he knew how
detrimental being special could be to
the soul Zen practice nobody is special
nobody's a star the practice is communal
but also a purely solitary
after the retreat and a celebratory
feast I brought home his left over land
chops which couldn't be kept at the
temple after a Zen monks life as a
vegetarian when Leonard was in Montreal
he went to a famous deli to get some
sacramental meat and liquor when I
brought the meat home I told my
roommates proudly these are Leonard
Cohen's leftover Leonard shops we ate
them in a silent all in admiration as if
they were a blessed substance that year
I wrote Leonard a letter by post I
addressed it to Mount Baldy Zen Center
where he was apparently living an
austere life and the letter I wrote
among other things I am your son I was
told that the letter caused a bit of
stir in the monastery but I never know
why it was pretty arrogant for me to say
that there was something true there too
we are all sons and daughters of the
artists we love the best and we are
doomed to imitate them until we can make
it real ourselves - old going home
meditations on Leonard Cohen number
three people who love Leonard Cohen
absque Ribe saint-like qualities to the
man but before we can annoys him perhaps
we should enlarge our notion of what is
a saint the buddhist jewish saint or
Buju might actually have a wild sense of
humor and be a bit of a hedonist he
might be an eccentric mensch
you dish for all-around super guy rather
than someone with an aura of holiness he
might not feed the lepers but still feed
those burning hearts and he'll
nonetheless the only time I saw Leonard
Cohen live was at his final show in
Paris in 2013 I had been afraid
beforehand that I might be disappointed
as he performs more or less the same set
every time and I've heard those songs a
million times in the end I couldn't have
been more wrong after the first couple
minutes tears began pouring from my eyes
I was struck by the fact that he was on
his knees maybe half
time you was seeing as if in worshipful
prayer those later shows had the uncanny
quality of a religious Advent as all
great collective expressions of art
should watching an early document tarry
on YouTube I got the sense that most
rock critics didn't really have a
adequate language to speak about Leonard
Cohen it helps to study spiritual and
poetic traditions if you want to go
deeper into the secret life Cohen sings
about although the resonance of his
songs will be present nonetheless
perhaps as one who stet has studied zen
a little bit i can be i can offer some
insight here it is japanese zen practice
there is a strict container for
meditation and work everything is
ritualized and one performs the same
gestures over and over again until they
become perfectly natural the paradox of
Zen is that real spontaneity cannot
exist without freedom but only within
limits the limits themselves are the
freedom as every artist knows although
each show in the Grand Tour was nearly
exactly the same Cohen was able to make
those songs anew every single night this
was different than in the early days of
his career when his performances
appeared painful assimilation a
parroting of feelings that had already
had their time he felt but Zen training
taught Cohen to perform from the zero
point as if for the first time each
moment perhaps that is why every concert
he did from the age of seven Eon was a
memorable event I've never spoken to
anyone who did not feel that way about
his later shows the remarkable thing
about those last tours was to see an
elderly man reached the summit of his
spiritual powers so late in life usually
such power is spent and wasted on youth
but Cohen actually seems to have
experienced a second life or a spiritual
rebirth at around 70 The Hunchback the
demon on his back the Beast with his
horn seems to have completely fallen
away and left him finally and totally
available to his audience
in those shows there was a sense that he
worshipped his audience as intensely as
they worshipped him the sympathy was
absolute the fact that the ban was a bit
campy only added to the charm Cohen
didn't need to be avant-garde because
the substance was there
he played slow and not too loud as in
the song I always liked it slow because
the audience was fully present to be at
those shows felt like going home to
court another song title unlike most of
his contemporaries Cohen never burned
out or became a nostalgic act his last
album is as good as the first
he showed that one's craft can be
refined purified deepened over a
lifetime that an artist life doesn't
have to be an early bloom followed by a
slow decay which is the typical American
outcome a lifetime artist blossoms has a
greater flower of spirit over time even
as the body falls apart the few other
songwriters with literary chops like Bob
Dylan Patti Smith Nick Cave Tom Waits
Lou Reed to name a few I've also endured
because they were poets I believe but
Cohen is in a different category the
former are poets on fire their style is
swaggering theatrical operatic ohm Eric
big they come from the school of Bob
Dylan's America where as Leonard Cohen
comes from that faraway country of ice
and snow he is a planet all of his own
Ben can Indian at home as one of the
songs isn't named Cohen is the opposite
forced to rock and roll
he is what your spirit craves when you
were tired of the sonic overload and
after the youthful excesses burned away
there is plenty of soul and corn but
there's almost no aggression there he's
never in a rush he has a broken voice
but he is at ease with brokenness the
Leonard Cohen after world as Kurt Cobain
sang
is a place where hubris has died Cohen
was absurdly modest almost embarrassed
to be a star but at the same time he
possessed a remarkable degree of
confidence this might be a peculiar
Canadian quality Canada the country
where vast northern spaces make no room
for the ego but let the spirit grow
large the individual melts into the
terrifying northern Beauty and vast wild
spaces is shattered against snow banks
that climate of Montreal where winters
are colder than Leningrad and summers
are sweltering hot with armies of
mosquitoes that may be the perfect
training ground for the Buju Saint in
any case if Cohen was a saint it was not
through poverty but plenitude and
generosity that made him one although he
did spend some time in a pretty harsh
aesthetic monastic environment of course
Cohen also sang about being a sinner
according to his last teacher rabbi
Jakob only a sinner can repair God
therefore only a sinner can be a saint
or no God in other words how does a
sinner like Cohen repair God by offering
up his sins his dualities his
complexities his contradictions his
suffering back to God through that form
of prayer called popular song the
wretched beast is tame meditations on
Leonard Cohen number 4
Dylan's achievement is so monumental he
was the Picasso
I'm the Matisse I love Matisse but I'm
in off a castle comparing Bob Dylan and
Leonard Cohen is to compare two
archetypes they are like alchemical
poles Dylan is all fire and speed and
creation he creates faster than he
thinks burns through forms and styles
with lightning intensity and
indifference to what is left behind
conversely Cohen is the deep earth the
slow bloom the melody calm
from the perfection of waiting intensity
concern and care for every syllable
Dylan is the hyperactive and electric of
American generative force Cohen is the
slow ballad of deep European roots and
soil Picasso like Dylan his brilliant
stuns blinds and seduces us it is
revolutionising in its spirit it's as it
is endless in his provocation
it is also endlessly frustrating and
elusive because we can't pin Dylan or
Picasso for that matter down when we
tire of that capricious youthful energy
of Picasso and seek repose we can count
on Suzanne's mountains and their depths
Susanne painted hundreds of the same
mount sainte-victoire similarily
a Cohen song is structurally and
thematically more or less a variation of
the same theme Cohen has only one theme
only one mountain but that mountain that
perspective like Suzanne's Mountain can
be regarded from every point of view in
my 20s and 30s I listen to Bob Dylan and
now in my 40s I listen to Leonard Cohen
Dylan resonates with a younger person a
person in their 20s and 30s is
gloriously narcissistic and
self-centered as Dylan obviously was the
young fail in love because they are
mostly in love with themselves in their
own creation their spirituality is
subjective
they haven't contemplated their own doom
sufficiently to feel that they are
anything other than immortal I don't
mean to criticize Dylan for he was truly
great as well his so-called protest
songs were always transcendental even if
he appeared to be writing about the
social issues of the day of course such
songs are relevant to the realm of
politics but are rooted in the self with
a capital S similarly in Cohen
politicking is not really the main
concern not to say that these singers
were indifferent to the happenings of
the world only as artists they work with
the sources of those concerns more than
outward manifestation deep art doesn't
have to take on events of the world
directly to illuminate in fact the
mistake of conceptual art is to be
overly literal a meaningless diary of
incidents both Bob Dylan and Cohen
tapped into a deeper mythological truth
than very day while youth is about fire
and energy the second or third act are
about coming home in that sense Dylan
and Picasso represent youth and cohen
and suzanne represent maturity we are in
awe of youth certainly it has its
glories but we learn about our doom
dylan saying its doom alone that counts
we need the strength that comes from
weariness with time cohen sang my love
aren't you tired yet in that weariness
in that darkness we find repose and a
deeper kind of force and illumination
that is not to say that dylan didn't do
great mature work as well he did but one
senses a certain devastation in his
later work which has a sublime beauty of
its own and yet we feel that he hasn't
quite slain the beast and cohen the
wretched beast is tame there was a sense
of reconciliation which he aim for and
achieves in his later career and this
kind of reconciliation as I have pointed
out several times in these essays is
quite rare most of us are still out
there fighting with that monumental
beast the Silent One meditations on
Leonard Cohen number 5 most singers do
their best work in early life in the
summit of their physical prowess Bob
Dylan for instance experienced quite a
few years of illuminated genius or
everything he wrote was inspired but we
feel his light dimmed somewhat over time
Dylan's best later work was colored by
nostalgia he never quite recovered the
brilliance of a song like a hard rain's
gonna fall
dillan mostly stop singing about the
future and instead sang about regret and
loss the Blues in other words but an
early song like hard rain was about the
world to come in other words the future
it was prophetic and poetic in the
biblical sense
Dylan seems to have lost that taste for
prophecy not to dismiss his very great
later works but he has turned his back
to the Future to sing about a forgotten
golden age Leonard Cohen on the other
hand is the inverse of Dylan arguably he
did his best work and definitely his
best performances in the final years and
Cohen never lost that prophetic
sharpness or his vision of the future he
was always looking forward I'll be it
with dread but with the steady
determination of a captain steering his
ship through dark water the future is
murder he sings and yet the future is
also revelation the bright soul is
revealed and blooms even in the nasty
business of aging and dying the future
is both disintegration and becoming and
Cohen embraced both why didn't Co and
lose that original spark as so many
artists do one answer may be a certain
hygiene he balanced hedonism with
intense bouts of monastic solitude he
balanced Fame with anonymity
vulnerability with toughness of thinking
pleasure with the consciousness of
suffering while serving a teacher
undoing Zen training seriously it was
less important for him to be Leonard
Cohen than Jihan which means the silent
one and this end is his Buddhist name I
sense the coin was running towards
anonymity rather than fame while Fame
was chasing after him I don't think
Dylan was chasing after Fame
particularly either but both were
looking for something more essential
they were on a spiritual quest we are
drawn to such artists even more when
they turn away from us and both Dylan
and Cohen were good
the disappearance act the deeper
ambition of a great artist isn't fame
but Transfiguration and transcendence
perfection of the sole means casting the
shackles of personality aside the person
is just a mask in the end as Cohen and
Dylan both knew well in interviews Cohen
was always deflecting one feels his
frustration when asked about his
personal life his extreme politeness was
surely a survival mechanism and with the
vampires of fame surrounding him he
rarely complain still you feel he was in
anguish when he wasn't being asked the
essential questions
sadly the average person just wants an
ice pop jingle and gossip about an
entertaining personality Cohen ever
hospitable give the audience that as
well Cohen had old-world manners
he wasn't condescending or defensive
even his fedora suits showed but he
treated his position seriously and not
casually he had the he had the ability
to make a somewhat ridiculous occasion
like an interview into something
intimate and beautiful his performances
had the same quality even in large
venues intimacy and humor I've seen the
future and it is murder meditations on
Leonard Cohen number six as soon as I
heard that Godzilla had been elected I
still believe it is unwise to give them
any more free advertising by mentioning
his name I put on the song democracy by
Leonard Cohen the next morning I found
out that Leonard had died at the age of
82 the future has some of Cohen's most
prophetic songs from the early 90s in it
he makes the obvious prediction that
things are going to slide in all
directions and yet despite the catalogue
of Horrors he envisions such as the
breaking of the Western code fires in
the road and the white man dancing a
woman hanging upside down her features
covered by
fallin gown the songs are somehow upbeat
and make you feel better
that is because truth no matter how
bleak its what the soul needs and wants
to hear and the truth is neither black
nor white as the song goes the truth is
complex and deep while letting the
recent election debacle sink in it
occurred to me in such genuine
apocalyptic times there is no more
appropriate instructive healing and
poetically truthful voice out there than
I can think of than Leonard Cohen many
people in the past have characterized
Cohen's work as depressive but at the
same time they put on his music in their
most aesthetic moments again I want to
repeat Cohen's songs are the antidote to
depression there is no more effective
medication that I can think of than
those songs especially now a couple
weeks before Cohen's death I wrote an
essay about meeting him and what his
music meant to me but since his death I
have realized that I wasn't done talking
to him yet if I can't write a Leonard
Cohen song and believe me I've tried the
next best thing might be to write a
commentary on his work sometimes it is
better to meditate on a work of art
rather than to make it and during times
of low energy and creation it's good to
listen to look Cohen for sustenance we
have to be careful not to become the
lousy little poets trying to sound like
Charlie Manson the Cohen spoke of in
democracy we should listen to a mature
and deeply intelligent voice like
Cohen's if today's society where
Godzilla and reality TV are at the helm
what we need are adults Cohen wrote
music for adults not overgrown babies of
American privilege and this is what the
future needs
mature beings to restore the humors of
life what does it mean that democracy is
coming to the USA doesn't mean that
democracy is the ultimate calamity well
certainly the fascist leaders of the
20th century were elected
pratically but that's not really the
point it might be best not to reach for
an answer to such questions instead hold
that statement there's a resonant
complexity what is this democracy Cohen
tells us democracy is both a boon and a
pestilence it's coming like the tidal
flood beneath the lunar sway Imperial
mysterious and amorous array democracy
is coming to the USA well it's here
democracy is the Whore of Babylon decked
out in all our finery
she is garish she is calamitous she is
the ultimate bitch Godzilla but as she
tears the world apart we have to finally
see that the heart has to open in a
fundamental way okay I'll say her name
just once
Donald she might be the terrible whore
Cohen sang about if you want to know
precisely why the maniacs in Trump Tower
will soon run the American machine go
and listen to the song democracy by
Leonard Cohen let me take this temple
down meditations on Leonard Cohen number
seven like the ancient troubadours who
sang the news through song Leonard Cohen
responded to traumatic global events
such as the fall of the Berlin Wall or
hurricane katrina through little
manifestos of the heart the news he sang
of was the spiritual news not a record
of facts and statistics but a deep
feeling response to the epic upheavals
in our world in the song samson in new
orleans he sings so gather up the
killer's get everyone in town stand me
by those pillars let me take this temple
down notice that cohen doesn't preach he
volunteers cohen will take that temple
of illusion the temple of the killers
down all by himself and saying these
things he is taking
responsibilities rather than casting
blame this tells me that he is deep in a
spiritual way because all deep
spirituality is fundamentally about
ultimate responsibility the revolution
cohen sings about is the secret one the
revolution of the heart when the
foundations of the house are rotten and
the imperial power has become the
ultimate horror of babylon what else is
there to do but do the spiritual work
oneself the horror has to be unroped
imaginatively not through blind and
violent revolution but through inner
conversion and we who cried for mercy
from the bottom of the pit was our
prayer so damned unworthy the son
rejected it this anguish interrogation
is not only from the american powers but
also for God does Jesus the son not hear
the prayers of the poor and destitute
why has God forsaken them why are the
innocent sacrificed in the engines of
power while the prodigal son sits on a
golden throne with his mouth full of
steak you can hear the anguish in
Cohen's voice in these later works a new
kind of emotion the anguish of
compassion the king is so kind and
solemn he wears a bloody crown so stand
me by that column let me take this
temple down there is the crown of
spiritual and the crown of worldly power
the crown of power rules over the
bloated Empire an imperial disarray
while the spiritual crown lies hidden in
the wreckage you said how could this
happen
you said how can this be the remnants
all dishonored on the bridge of misery
Dishonored maybe a polite word for rape
here the rape of the world by
mismanagement we are talking about a
violation a two-fold violation by
and also nature we stand on the bridge
between militarism and the crushing
mauve nature and her storms where is
mercy and love intelligence and wisdom
there
imagine the helpless people of Hurricane
Katrina being pushed further deeper into
the pit of misery doubly helpless
against nature and an affluent class
which protects the privileged and leaves
its poor behind a drown you said you
loved her secrets and her freedoms hid
away she was better than America that's
what I heard you say New Orleans here is
the soul of America she is better than
America she is the spiritual power of
America found in jazz music the greatest
art form America has given the world New
Orleans represents the land of real soul
in the midst of a phantasmagorical
shopping mall wasteland one would hope
America or sense and the strong man with
it's bloody crown and shorn head would
weep with remorse for what it is done to
the world not so the golden headed devil
is riding high and there's going to be
an even more terrible storm this is the
denial of love of homeland of Reason of
goodness where nothing can be measured
anymore let us finally take down the
temple of a bully America and find that
real land of plenty for the temple is
actually a Tinseltown horror house
filled with harlots and Philistines
there's a woman in the window there's a
bed in Tinseltown you said how could
this happen you said how can this be the
chains are gone from heaven the storms
are wild and free how could this happen
indeed and yet the impossible can and
will happen New Orleans after a terrible
storm was shorn by government henchmen
and profit tears human corruption is as
much to blame as nature
the dams were improperly constructed for
instance is America broken or is
democracy coming to the USA a dangerous
new clown Antichrist is sitting in the
White House throne of blood with the
nuclear codes so let us take this temple
down